A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Cali, Colombia, RG 6, SG 9 FA397
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, field offices, Cali, Colombia, RG 6, SG 9
1960-1978, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller Foundation. Cali (Colombia)
FA397
4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes
Scope and Contents note
Important Subjects
Developing countries--technical assistance --Medical education--Colombia --Public health--Colombia --Tropical medicine--Colombia --Colombia--Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations --Latin America--technical assistance --Rockefeller Foundation--Colombia
File Plan note
RG 6.9.
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices include:
FA395 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Paris.
FA396 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, New Delhi, India.
FA398 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Mexico.
FA399 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Office, Ankara, Turkey.
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 20 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
The Rockefeller Foundation opened a field office in Cali, Colombia in 1960, ten years after the establishment of the Colombian Agricultural Program in Bogota. Guy S. Hayes, an Assistant Director in the Medical and Natural Sciences division, held the post of Field Director in Cali from 1960 until 1970. After 1970, the office was headed by Foundation Representatives Patrick N. Owens (1970-1974) and Farzam Arbab (1974-78). The office closed on December 31, 1983.
RF activity in Colombia reflected the broad reorientation of Foundation programming away from Europe and towards the developing world which took place under RF Presidents Dean Rusk (1952-1961) and J. George Harrar (1961-1972). In Latin America, as in Africa and Southeast Asia, the Foundation sought to relieve basic human needs by establishing rural and community development programs, strengthening disease research facilities, and revitalizing universities that they might become more responsive to local populations. The RF approach to development involved the training of local personnel and the strengthening of local institutions through exchange programs with American universities and fellowships support for Colombian scholars.
One of the prime beneficiaries of RF support in Colombia was the Universidad del Valle and its Medical School at Cali, which received assistance under the RF's University Development program (1963-1978). (The program was renamed Education for Development (EFD) in 1974). The Universidad del Valle became one of the best medical schools in Latin America, combining the practice of public health at the Candelaria Rural Health Center with the teaching and practice of medicine. The EFD program was phased out in 1978, with future university grants made within the appropriate RF program areas.
Arrangement note
The Cali office records are arranged in four series:
Series 1 - Administrative Correspondence; Series 2 - Universidad del Valle--Academic Programs; Series 3 - Universidad del Valle--Medical Programs; Series 4 - Cooperating Universities and Programs.
Within series, files are arranged in the order received, according to an internal numeric system. Retaining the files' original order preserves the usefulness of numerous cross-reference inserts that refer to related files by number. Gaps in the numbering sequence indicate that the office discarded portions of these records prior to their transfer to New York in 1977, 1978, and 1984.
Folders are arranged by file number. File numbers appear in parentheses following folder title.
Scope and Contents note
The records (1960-1978) of the Rockefeller Foundation's Cali, Colombia field office, consisting of routine administrative correspondence, document to a limited extent the administration of the RF's Education for Development (EFD) program and other programs undertaken in Colombia by the RF's divisions of Medical and Natural Sciences and Humanities and Social Sciences.
While the focus of the Bogota office was agriculture, the Cali office coordinated programs in rural, community, and university development. Series I contains eight folders concerning the Cali field station of the RF's Virus Research Program (1964-73), a program for research on arthropod-borne (arbo) viruses. The bulk of the collection, located in Series II and III, relates to the development of the University del Valle's Academic and library programs and its medical school under the auspices of the RF's University Development (1963-74) and Education For Development (1974-78) programs. Series IV includes correspondence between the Cali staff and several American universities cooperating with the Universidad del Valle in rural and tropical disease research, preventitive medicine and nutrition, and child and public health.
Correspondents include Farzam Arbab, Ulysses J. Grant, Guy S. Hayes, Robert S. Morison, Patrick N. Owens, Dorothy Parker, Virgil C. Scott, Harold Trapido, John Veenstra, and John M. Weir. Some correspondence is in Spanish.
Scope and Contents note
Important Names
Arbab, Farzam --Grant, Ulysses J. --Hayes, Guy S. --Morison, Robert S. --Owens, Patrick N. --Parker, Dorothy --Scott, Virgin C. --Trapido, Harold --Veenstra, John --Weir, John
Related Archival Materials note
For information about specific grants to individuals or institutions in Colombia, consult the grant files located in Record Group 1.1 and 1.2 (Projects), 311 (Colombia), in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives.
Social sciences -- India; Public health; Philanthropy; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Agriculture -- India; Agriculture; Agricultural innovations -- Mexico; Agricultural innovations; Medical research -- India; Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Life sciences; Latin America; Philanthropy -- United States; India; Green Revolution; Colombia; Charities
- Administrative Correspondence, 1960-1977; 1; 1.2 cubic feet
  - Bogota Office (210), 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (211), 1960-1965, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Staffing and Personnel (214), 1960-1962, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Staffing and Personnel (214), 1960-1962, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Staffing and Personnel (214), 1960-1962, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Staffing and Personnel (214A), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Staffing and Personnel (214A), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Visiting Firemen (216), 1967, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Visiting Firemen (216), 1967, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Foreign Students Program (225), 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (RF) Virus Program (228), 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (RF) Virus Program (228), 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (RF) Virus Program (228), 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - RF Virus Program (228), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - RF Virus Program (228), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - RF Virus Program (228), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - RF Virus Program (228), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - RF Virus Program (228), 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Centro Internacional De Agricultura Tropical (230), 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Centro Internacional De Agricultura Tropical (230), 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Centro de Recursos Para la Ensenanza (231), 1970-1971, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - World Health Organization (232), 1970-1971, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Fundacion Para La Educacion SUperior (233), 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Departamento de Investigaciones y Educacion -- Proyectos Especiales (233A), 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Departamento de Investigaciones y Educacion -- Proyectos Especiales (233A), 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Asociacion Nacional para la Defensa de la Naturaleza (ANADENA) (234), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Instituto Colombiano Agropecuario (235), 1973, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Programa de Invetigacion en Modelos de Prestacion de Servicios de Salud (PRIMOPS) (236), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Universidad del Valle--Academic Programs, 1962-1975, n.d.; 2; 1.2 cubic feet
  - General Correspondence (400), 1966-1967, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - General Correspondence (400), 1966-1967, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - General Correspondence (400), 1966-1967, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Department of Sociology (404A), 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Department of Sociology - Cauca Valley Study (404B), 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Nursing Education (405), 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Nursing Education (405), 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Nursing Education (405), 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Nursing Education - School of Nursing Program (405), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Nursing Education - Auxiliary Nursing Course (405A), 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Political Science Department (406), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Agricultural Economics (406B), 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Division of Humanities (407), 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Basic Studies Program (408), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Language Department (409), 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Library Program (410), 1964-1974 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Library Program (410), 1964-1974 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Library Program (410), 1964-1974 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Faculty of Engineering (411), 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Faculty of Engineering (411), 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Faculty of Engineering (411), 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Faculty of Engineering (411), 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Faculty of Engineering (411), 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Faculty of Engineering - Centro de Calculo Electronico (411A), 1971-1973, 1975, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Faculty of Engineering - Agricultural Engineering (411B), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Faculty of Architecture (412), 1967-1970, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Faculty of Architecture (412), 1967-1970, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Division of Sciences (413), 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Division of Sciences (413), 1968-1976 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Faculty of Education (414), 1968, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Operations Research (415), 1966-1970, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Operations Research (415), 1966-1970, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Sanitary Engineering (416), 1968-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Sanitary Engineering (416), 1968-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Sanitary Engineering (416), 1968-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Sanitary Engineering (416), 1968-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Sanitary Engineering (416), 1968-1971, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Department of Physics (417), 1969-1971, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Biology Department (418), 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Department of Industrial Administration (419), 1972 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Natural Resources Program (420), 1973 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Onchocerciasis Control (421), 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 78)
- Universidad del Valle--Medical Programs, 1960-1976, 1978; 3; 0.8 cubic feet
  - Faculty of Medicine - General (500), 1963-1966, 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    General note
    See also below, Faculty of Medicine - Department of Internal Medicine, folder 95.
  - Faculty of Medicine - General (500), 1963-1966, 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Faculty of Medicine - General (500), 1963-1966, 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - International Development Research Center, Canada (501), 1972-1974, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Fundacion Nacional para la Desarrollo Social (FUNDES) (502), 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Del Valle University Hospital - General (503), 1961-1967, 1972, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Del Valle University Hospital - General (503), 1961-1967, 1972, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Medical Center (503), 1966-1969 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Metabolic Unit (51), 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Preventive Medicine and Public Health - General (540), 1961-1966, 1969-1970, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Preventive Medicine and Public Health - General (540), 1961-1966, 1969-1970, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Preventive Medicine and Public Health - Programa de Investigaciones en Planeacion de Salud (COLINPLAS) (540A), 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Programa UV-ICA-CIAT (Universidad del Valle - Instituto Colombiano Agropecuario - Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical) (540B), 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Canadian Program (541), 1971 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Candelaria Program (543/604), 1965-1966, 1968-1969, 1973-1974, 1976, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Candelaria Program (543/604), 1965-1966, 1968-1969, 1973-1974, 1976, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Faculty of Medicine - Department of Internal Medicine (570), 1960-1966 (Box 8, Folder 95)
- Cooperating Universities and Programs, 1960-1976; 4; 1.2 cubic feet
  - General Correspondence (600), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Universidad Federal de Bahia (601), 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Universidad Federal de Bahia (601), 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Universidad Federal de Bahia (601), 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Harvard University - Cali Project - General Correspondence (604), 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Harvard University - Cali Project - Statistics (604D), 1960-1961, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - St. Lucia Project (605), 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - St. Lucia Project (605), 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - St. Lucia Project (605), 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - University of Notre Dame Program (606), 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - University of Tennessee Program (607), 1960-1970 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - University of Tennessee Program (607), 1960-1970 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - University of Tennessee Program (607), 1960-1970 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - University of Tennessee Program (607), 1960-1970 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - University of Florida Program (608), 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - University of Florida Program (608), 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - University of Florida Program (608), 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - University of Florida Program (608), 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - University of Florida Program (608), 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Cornell University Program (609), 1966-1970, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Cornell University Program (609), 1966-1970, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Cornell University Program (609), 1966-1970, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Yale University Program (610), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Centro de Investigaciones Multidisciplinarios en Salud (CIMS) (611), 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - The Mitre Corporation (612), 1973 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Tulane University - International Center for Medical Research and Training (701), 1963-1967, 1969-1976 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Tulane University - International Center for Medical Research and Training (701), 1963-1967, 1969-1976 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Tulane University - International Center for Medical Research and Training (701), 1963-1967, 1969-1976 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Ford Foundation (706), 1965-1968, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Colegio Bolivar (709), 1966, 1968-1972, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Colegio Bolivar (709), 1966, 1968-1972, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Colegio Bolivar (709), 1966, 1968-1972, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Centro Colombo Americano (710), 1962-1972 (Box 11, Folder 128)